All right, I'm going to be completely
honest with you. The tech job market
right now isn't cooked. The standard is
just raised significantly. The required
talent and skills to get you an
entry-level software engineering role
paying $90,000 a year is completely
different now compared to 10 years ago.
I've been watching developers with five
plus years of experience get rejected
from junior positions. I've seen boot
camp graduates with perfect portfolios
go months without a single interview.
The reason is because everyone is using
the same outdated methods that just
don't work today. I'm not going to get
into it in this video. If you want to
know more about what works today, you
can watch my other videos.
I want to talk about a different
opportunity, a different path software
engineers can take to make same income
as a normal dev job. Wilts also
experienced the location and time
freedom that everyone seems to be
working towards since co. What nobody's
talking about is while everyone's
fighting over the same shrinking pool of
traditional tech jobs, there's this
massive opportunity sitting right in
front of us that most developers
completely ignore. In the next 10
minutes or so, I'll break down why
freelance devs are making a killing and
how you can do the same to reclaim
control of time and income in a way
that's different to the traditional
path. I know my whole channel has been
about landing tech jobs, but what you
probably didn't know was I was also a
freelance software engineer, too. As
nice as it is to have a stable income
from a traditional job and normal
9-to-five hours, freelancing also has
its pros, too. You work as much as you
want, work whatever hours you want, and
technically have no income cap. And with
how brutally competitive the tech job
market is now, with companies laying off
experienced developers while
simultaneously posting job listings they
never intend to fill. with AI tools
making employers think they need fewer
developers with the ones that are hiring
wanting entry-level developers to have
five plus years experience even though
that doesn't really make sense.
Statistically, it's impossible for every
aspiring dev to get a role working at a
big firm unless you got me as a mentor.
I have had students come to me with
solid portfolios, great technical
skills, who've been job hunting for
eight plus months with nothing to show
for it. Not because they're not good
enough, but because they're playing a
rigged game. Meanwhile, I've been
quietly freelancing on the side for
years. During my time freelancing, I was
making $15,000 in pure take-home from
freelance projects, working maybe 20
hours total. What surprised me was that
small businesses are desperate for
developers. While big tech is laying
people off, every local business needs a
website, an app, some kind of digital
solution. They have money, they have
problems, and they don't care if you
went to Stanford or learn to code last
year. They just want someone who can
solve their problems professionally. But
here's where most people get this
completely wrong. Everyone thinks
freelancing is about competing on price
on Upwork. charging $15 an hour to build
someone's WordPress site. That's not
freelancing. That's digital slavery.
Real freelancing is about becoming the
technical co-founder these businesses
can't afford to hire full-time. It's
about packaging your skills into
solutions, not selling your time by the
hour. While everyone else is trying to
get hired, you're going to get hired by
multiple companies at once. Instead of
hoping one company values you at $80,000
a year, you're going to have five
companies each paying you $2,000 a month
for ongoing work. Same money, but you're
in control. And that changes everything.
The modern freelancing reality. Now, I
know because the last time I did
freelance work was last year.
Re to give you a little update about my
life. Recently, I am working recently,
but not a full-time job. I'm uh helping
out a friend. He started his own company
and he got um he got some contract with
some government that's helping out a
manufacturing execution system and I'm
making the chatbot and it's uh it's it's
a challenge and I'm I'm I'm up for any
challenge really. Um
so I've made a lot of progress on that.
And another update, you know, uh I
haven't shaved since I've uh been laid
off, uh you know, for like the 6 to 8
weeks that I've been laid off. People
are going to come at me in the comments
saying things like, "He did this x years
ago. What he's saying won't work now, or
the freelance market is so much more
saturated now. I have mentees making
successful careers as freelancers right
now." Ultimately led to me finally
landing uh my first freelance job. Uh I
Phil made a connection uh to somebody
who was a ex CMO I think of IKEA which
was the uh website that I made for him
and ever since then we've kind of kept
open communications and anything that
needs for the website or maybe something
else he's looking at creating or even
some random like business solution types
things that another company might ask
him for. I've been able to dip my toe in
that provide some quick solutions. With
that in mind, let me break down how
freelancing actually works in 2025
because everything has changed. First,
the AI tools like Claude and Kitup
Copilot have cut development time in
half. This may sound scary, like you
don't stand a chance, but this is your
advantage. You can now deliver projects
twice as fast, which means you can serve
more clients or charge premium rates for
speed. I watched a senior developer
charge $30 an hour because he was
competing on time. Meanwhile, I charge
$2,000 for an MVP that takes me 10 hours
to build with AI assistance. Same work,
completely different framing.
Pillar one, solution over
specialization. Here's the beautiful
thing about freelancing. There's not so
much pressure on being a specialist
compared to the traditional job market.
If you can create the desired solution,
no one cares what language you used or
how your code looks. Understanding the
scope of work required for the solution
is way more important than technical
perfection. This means really
understanding your target market, what
problems they face, what solutions they
need, and how much those solutions are
worth to them. Pillar two, package.
Don't price. Stop charging hourly.
Instead of I charge $50 an hour for
development, I'll build you a complete
e-commerce solution for $5,000. The key
things to remember is that you're not
selling features. You're selling
benefits. Don't say, "I'll build you a
website with five pages and a contact
form." Say, "I'll build you a system
that captures leads 24/7 and converts
visitors into paying customers." Same
work, but now you're selling the
outcome, not the process. Pillar three,
underpromise overd deliver. The only way
to build a long-term freelance business
is by delivering a damn good product or
service. If your product is good, it'll
do the selling for you. You can build a
book of business through referrals.
Build social proof and eventually have
people come to you instead of the other
way around. One amazing project beats 10
mediocre ones every single time.
Step one, identify your target market,
especially in the beginning. It's easier
to serve one market since there's less
variability in your scope of work for
each project. If the first market
doesn't work, move to the next. Don't
try to be everything to everyone right
away. Step two, build your portfolio.
Just like the traditional job market,
you need projects to show you can do the
job. Build examples that directly solve
problems your target market faces. I've
mentioned this multiple times throughout
my other videos, but it's really that
simple in order to get noticed. People
want to visualize what you can do. Step
three, master selling and presenting.
Here's what most developers don't
realize. Delivering a good product isn't
enough on its own to build a freelancing
business. You need to know how to sell
and present your solution. Well, this is
a skill you have to develop, just like
coding. Step four, rinse and repeat.
Keep refining your approach until you
get your first couple of customers. Then
use those wins to build momentum for the
next ones.
It sounds simple because it is. Think
about it this way. A small business will
pay $300 to $800 monthly for digital
solutions, but a midsize company will
pay $3,000 to $8,000 monthly for the
same type of work because the impact is
proportionally bigger. Businesses need
ongoing projects, too. System upgrades,
new features, seasonal campaigns,
integration work. A small client is
worth $1 to $3,000 annually beyond
retainers. A bigger client would be
around $10 to $50,000 annually in
project work. I have a friend who
started with one pizza shop, built them
an ordering system that led to a
regional pizza chain contract worth
$150,000 annually. Same core skills, but
he learned to think bigger. That's the
power of starting small but scaling
smart.
Common mistakes that kill your success.
Mistake one, competing on price. Never
be the cheapest option. Be the most
professional, most reliable option.
Cheap clients are nightmare clients.
Mistake two, over complicating the tech.
They don't care if you use React or
vanilla JavaScript. They care if it
works, loads fast, and makes them money.
Mistake three, forgetting the business
side. You're spending 50% of your time
coding, 50% managing clients, marketing,
and admin. Plan for this reality or
you'll burn out fast. I feel like it's
important to reiterate that the tech job
market isn't actually saturated. It's
just broken. Companies are posting
impossible job requirements because they
don't understand what they actually
need. They want 3 plus years experience
for entry-level roles because HR
departments are using outdated filters
that made sense in 2015. But freelancing
gives you a different playing field
entirely. You're not competing with
1,000 other developers for one position.
You're the only developer talking to
this specific restaurant owner about
their specific problem. And here's the
beautiful part. You can do both. Keep
applying for jobs while building your
freelance income. Worst case scenario,
you have multiple income streams. Best
case scenario, your freelance income
becomes so good, you never need a
traditional job. Think about it this
way. Instead of hoping one company will
pay you $100,000 annually, you could
have 20 clients each paying you $500
monthly. That's $120,000 annually and
you're the boss. Why this works even
better now? The remote work revolution
made small businesses realize they don't
need local developers. But it also made
them realize most developers don't
understand their business. If there's
anything you should take away from this
video, it's that you're not just a
developer. You're a problem solver.
You're someone who can take a business's
vision and turn it into reality. Every
business owner I've worked with has the
same story. They had an idea. They
needed technical help and they were
willing to pay well for someone who
actually understood both the technical
and business sides. The tech job market
might be broken, but the demand for real
solutions has never been higher. While
everyone else is fighting for permission
to prove their worth, you can start
proving your worth this week. The choice
is yours. Keep playing the game where
you have no control or start playing the
game where you make the rules. The
opportunity is there. The framework
works. Stop waiting for someone else to
give you a chance and start creating
your own chances. If you found this
helpful, subscribe for more honest
career advice. Go build something real.
The market is waiting for you. Coding
saves lives.