In the past 18 months, more than 170,000
tech workers in the United States have
lost their jobs. Used car startup Kavak
is the latest global tech name to cut
jobs. In the first 5 months of 2025
alone, more than 74,000 layoffs were
recorded in tech companies, representing
a 35% increase compared to the same
period the previous year. Meta has never
axed jobs on this scale before. 11,000
positions were about 13% of its
workforce. In fields like programming,
the losses are even more alarming.
Between 2022 and 2024, 27% of jobs in
this area disappeared, according to
official data. Jeffrey Hinton, the
so-called godfather of AI and a pioneer
in the field, warns some industries may
be hit harder than others. At the same
time, average tech salaries have fallen
by more than 12% nationwide. All of this
has led tech workers to question whether
the industry is still worth it. So,
where are all the tech workers going?
Mass layoffs in tech have not only
reduced staff numbers, but also
triggered significant labor migration.
Thousands of highly skilled workers have
been forced to seek new opportunities
outside the traditional tech sector.
Some individuals have managed to quickly
rejoin smaller companies or take on
similar roles, though often with less
favorable compensation. Others have
chosen to switch industries, start their
own ventures, or pursue further
education or professional development
programs. Even though the overall
unemployment rate in the United States
has remained around 4.2% during the
first half of 2025, the impact on tech
employment has been significant. Layoffs
are only above average in three sectors,
tech, finance, and trucking. While the
specific unemployment rate in the tech
sector was 3.4% 4% in May. This figure
does not reflect the drop in entry-level
hiring. It also fails to capture the
increase in precarious work conditions
such as freelancing or temporary
contracts. Among those who lost their
jobs, about half managed to reenter the
labor market within 6 months. However,
the types of jobs they found often
differed from their previous roles. Only
32% were able to return to tech
companies, usually smaller or less
established ones. The rest transitioned
into sectors such as finance, consulting
or manufacturing. As major companies
like Meta, Google, Salesforce, and more
cut thousands of jobs, other companies,
some smaller, some in different sectors,
were eager to bring in new talent.
Abbott, for example, has hired more than
200 tech specific employees in the past
6 months. And a company spokesperson
says they plan to hire hundreds more in
the coming years. According to various
studies, around 10% of these workers
move into the financial industry where
there is sustained demand for
professionals with experience in
systems, data, and security. Another 8%
join consulting firms while
approximately 6% find opportunities in
the healthcare sector, an area
undergoing rapid digital transformation.
Others are employed by logistics or
manufacturing companies that are
adopting smart technologies to optimize
operations. In this context, the use of
buyouts or voluntary exit programs has
become common in large tech companies, a
strategy that allows for discrete
workforce reductions without resorting
to formal layoffs. Under this model,
employees are offered financial
compensation to voluntarily leave their
positions, helping companies avoid
negative headlines and minimize
reputational damage. Although framed as
voluntary, these packages are often
strategically targeted at specific roles
or departments. Companies like Google,
Meta, and Salesforce have adopted this
practice over the past 2 years, offering
severance packages that include extra
weeks of pay, extended benefits, and job
placement assistance. Google is offering
buyouts to employees across several of
its divisions, including the unit that
houses its search, ad, and commerce
businesses. The decline in opportunities
at major tech firms has also fueled a
rise in self-employment. Platforms such
as Upwork, Fiverr, and TopTel have
become common channels for offering
professional services in software
development, data analysis, or system
maintenance. This model offers some
flexibility, but does not guarantee
financial stability or access to
traditional benefits. For many,
freelance work serves as a temporary
solution while they develop a new career
strategy or acquire more in- demand
skills. At the same time, there has been
growing interest in entrepreneurship.
Some workers, particularly those with
more experience and access to funding
networks, have used severance pay or
savings to launch startups. These
ventures often focus on emerging areas
such as educational technology, digital
health, or decentralized financial
services. Another path that has gained
relevance in recent months is the
transition of tech workers into the
public sector, particularly in areas
related to cyber security. The
Department of Defense, the Cyber
Security and Infrastructure Security,
and other government agencies have
intensified their hiring efforts to
strengthen systems against growing
digital threats. This shift represents
an opportunity for those seeking greater
job stability, and a sense of public
mission. While government salaries are
generally lower than those in the
private sector, many professionals value
the improved work life balance,
long-term benefits, and the chance to
contribute to national security using
their technical expertise. The
adaptation process to this new landscape
has also involved a strong emphasis on
continued education. Many professionals
are turning to certifications and
intensive programs in areas like
artificial intelligence due to its
growing presence across a wide range of
industries. Cars that drive themselves,
facial recognition, detecting cancer
potentially better than a doctor. These
are just some of the technologies that
artificial intelligence is fueling.
Specialized courses on platforms such as
Google Cloud, TensorFlow, or Python have
grown in popularity along with graduate
programs at universities focused on
technology and business. This trend
reflects a collective effort to remain
relevant in an increasingly competitive
and specialized market where general
knowledge or traditional work experience
is no longer enough. However, the
process of re-entering the job market
has not been uniform. There are
significant disparities based on gender,
age, and prior experience. Among those
laid off from tech companies, women have
faced greater challenges. Only 31%
secured a new job within 3 months
compared to 38% of men. Mid-career
professionals have also encountered more
difficulties due to perceptions of
outdated skills or bias in recruitment
processes. At the same time, recent
graduates face a restrictive job market
with entry- level openings down 50%
since 2023. This summer, college
graduates in America are looking for
hire at a time when their unemployment
rate is at 6%. That's nearly 2% higher
than the overall national average.
Companies justify this reduction with
budget constraints and a growing trend
toward automating low complexity tasks.
The result of this phenomenon is an
increasingly segmented tech job market.
On one hand, there is high demand for
highly qualified profiles with expertise
in artificial intelligence, systems
architecture, advanced automation, and
data analytics. On the other hand,
access to entry-level roles and
generalist positions is narrowing,
creating a divide between those already
established in the industry and those
trying to enter for the first time. But
this divide is also reflected in
salaries. While some senior
professionals continue to earn over
$200,000 a year in markets like San
Francisco or New York, average wages
have declined nationwide, particularly
affecting those in transition or at the
start of their careers. The top tech
companies are facing hiring freezes and
layoffs due to cost cutting measures.
This new scenario presents challenges
not only for workers, but also for
educational institutions and policy
makers. There is a growing need to
promote reskilling programs, incentives
for hiring new talent, and social
protection schemes for independent
workers. Additionally, it is essential
to ensure transparency in layoff and
hiring processes, as well as to
facilitate mechanisms for labor mobility
across sectors that make full use of
this highly qualified workforce.
[Music]
At Economy Media, your opinion matters
to us. Subscribe and let us know what
you think in the comments below.